Tianyi Zhang

zty@seas.upenn.edu | https://tianyi0608.github.io/tianyizhang

HIGHLIGHTS

Expertise: Human Cognition 6 years in B.S., M.Ed.

Natural Language Processing 3 years in MSE

Research Experience: 4 projects in 3 years: Synopsis:

Event Extraction DARPA BETTER, 20-22, member, publication [2] Schema Induction DARPA KAIROS, 22-23, leader, publication [1] Entity-State Tracking AI2, 23 spring, member & leader, publication [3]

Natural to Symbolic Reasoning Ongoing

• **Research Interests:** Reasoning in Natural & Symbolic Language

Interdisciplinary in NLP, CV, and Robotics

Happy to explore and confident to work well in varied tasks

EDUCATION

• University of Pennsylvania | Philadelphia, America Sept. 2018 – Dec. 2022

MSE in Data Science GPA: 3.97/4.00

Advisors: Prof. Dan Roth, Prof. Chris Callison-Burch

M.Ed. in Learning Science and Technology GPA: 3.91/4.00

Advisor: Prof. Yasmin B. Kafai

• **Beijing Normal University** | Beijing, China

B.S. in Educational Technology GPA: 88/100

Advisor: Prof. Qian Fu

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Zhang, T.***, Tham, I. *, Hou, Z. *, Ren, J., Zhou, L., Xu, H., Zhang, L., Martin, L., Dror, R., Li, S., Ji, H., Palmer, M., Brown, S., Suchocki, R., and Callison-Burch, C. (2023). Human-in-the-Loop Schema Induction. In Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 3: System Demonstrations).
- [2] Zhang, T., Sulem, E., Roth, D. Question-Answering Data Augmentation for Argument Role Labeling. In submission
- [3] **Zhang, T.***, Zhang, L.*, Hou, Z., Wang, Z., Gu, Y., Clark, P., Callison-Burch, C., and Tandon, N. PROC2PDDL: Towards Open-Domain Symbolic Planning. In submission

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

• Current Research Oct. 2023 –

Natural to Symbolic Reasoning

- To enhance human reasoning on events
- · Design approaches imitate human knowledge acquisition, storage, and application
- · Process Natural Language request and infer on Symbolic Language (e.g., Python, PDDL)
- · Improve faithfulness and interpretability of LM reasoning

• NLP Group at UPenn

May. 2022 – Jun. 2023

Sept. 2014-Jul. 2018

Entity-State Tracking

- · To reason on events unfold: infer events with fine-grained entity-state
- Translate open-domain Natural Language text (wikiHow) to Symbolic Language (PDDL) with GPT-4

- · Decompose the task into three stages: extraction, inference, and translation
- · Identify strong text extraction and entity-state inference abilities with complex wikiHow text (~5000 words)
- · Acknowledge a weak translation capability to predefined symbolic predicates
- Improve the entity-state tracking using CoT and instructions on translation.
- Publication [3]: "PROC2PDDL: Towards Open-Domain Symbolic Planning"

Event Schema Induction

- · To understand event relations: (semi-) automatically create event schema in high quality
- Design the scaffolds (cause, plan, procedure, effect, etc.) for GPT-3
- · Apply SRL and constituency parsing to summarize and extract structured events
- Build schema graphs by adding temporal relations to the events
- Iteratively prompt LM and merge graphs
- · Design interface for human GPT interactive schema generation
- Improve accuracy and efficiency (1 hour to 15 mins per schema) and adopted by the UIUC group
- · Publication [1]: "Human-in-the-Loop Schema Induction"

Cognitive Computation Group at UPenn

Mar. 2020 - Dec. 2022

Event Extraction

- · To understand atomic events: extract events with 'who does what to whom'
- · Identify and classify event triggers using sequence tagging
- · Design a pipeline: BIO identify event type classify model to replace the joint model
- · Improve performance with transfer learning on target language dataset, e.g., OntoNotesArabic
- Identify and classify event arguments using QA
- Design fixed questions for each argument role and convert the argument role labeling task to the Question-Answering task
- Build a pipeline model: has/no answer classification + has answer identification to replace has-and-no-answer joint model
- Improve performance with transfer learning on auxiliary QA datasets, e.g., SQuAD, QAMR

Event Data Augmentation

- · To overcome the deficiency of event annotation data
- Design a pipeline approach: answer extraction (AE) and question generation (QG)
- Train AEwSRL-QG Bert-T5 model to extract QA pairs from unlabeled event text
- · Evaluate the augmented data on QA event extraction model
- Prove the effectiveness of the data augmentation approach (8k synthetic data exceeds 80k SQuAD data test on the ACE)
- Publication [2]: "Question-Answering Data Augmentation for Argument Role Labeling"

INTERNSHIP

• Research Assistant NLP Group at UPenn May. 2022 – Jun. 2023

See the Research Experience section for details

Cognitive Computation Group at UPenn Mar. 2020 – Dec. 2022

See the Research Experience section for details

Teaching Assistant CIS522 Deep Learning

Jan. 2022-May. 2022

- Design course materials and teach deep learning models in CV, NLP, RL, etc.
- · Hold Office Hours and group discussions each week.

Data Analyst SciStarter in Philadelphia

Sep. 2018-Apr. 2019

- Use the Python Pandas package to clean and analyze email log-in data (30,000 records).
- Find the highest possibility of emails being checked is between 9 a.m. to 3 p.m., and within 1 day (over 80%). The most attractive topics are love, games, and high tech. The royalty of the subscriber is 50%.